<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of W.P. from the erronious [sic] and false testimony of Thomas Budd: being in answer to a sheet of his, entituled, A testimony for truth, against error. / By Joseph Wyeth.</title>
            <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683584</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47683584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2661:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of W.P. from the erronious [sic] and false testimony of Thomas Budd: being in answer to a sheet of his, entituled, A testimony for truth, against error. / By Joseph Wyeth.</title>
                  <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</term>
               <term>Budd, Thomas, 1648-1699. --  Testimony for truth, against error.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173039:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF <hi>W. P.</hi> FROM THE Erronious and Falſe Teſtimony OF Thomas Budd: BEING In Anſwer to a Sheet of his, ENTITULED, <hi>A Teſtimony for Truth, againſt Error.</hi> By <hi>Joſeph Wyeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> next Door to the <hi>Meeting-houſe</hi> in <hi>VVhite-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet;</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet,</hi> near the <hi>Market,</hi> 1697.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173039:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:173039:2"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF <hi>W. P.</hi> FROM THE Erronious and Falſe Teſtimony OF <hi>T. B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DD;</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving met with a Sheet, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Teſtimony for Truth againſt Error,</hi> Subſcribed <hi>Thomas Budd,</hi> in which he Charges <hi>W. P.</hi> with denying ſome of the Chief Principles of Chriſtianity: After Reading the Sheet, I was very deſirous to get thoſe Books of <hi>W. P</hi>'s mentioned by <hi>T. Budd,</hi> that I might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Quotations from which he pretends to draw this Charge of Error; accordingly I did (with ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) get them, and have Examined the Pages refer'd to by <hi>T. Budd,</hi> and have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173039:3"/> juſt reaſon to be Amazed, that after ſuch picking, leaving out, and ſometimes forging <hi>W. P</hi>'s Adverſaries Words for <hi>W. P</hi>'s; a Man ſhould have ſo hard a Fore-head as to Entitule it, <hi>A Teſtimony for Truth;</hi> when in truth, it is a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of as great Villany as one Man can be capable of towards another; and nothing but Malice and Apoſtacy could be the Parent of ſo Monſtruous a Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which yet I know cannot at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence thoſe who know, and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſider the different Caracters and Qualities of <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>T. Budd:</hi> But to ſome who know them not otherwiſe, than as this Erronious Teſtimony againſt Truth repreſents, may (not having the Books to examine) take this Monſter of a Draught for <hi>W. P</hi>'s True Figure. For the Information of ſuch (and now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Books by me) as alſo to do Juſtice to <hi>W. P.</hi> I have undertaken this, wherein I ſhall do little more than to ſet down the places as they are quoted by <hi>T. Budd,</hi> and then ſubjoyn the places as they are in <hi>W. P</hi>'s Books, &amp; which will be found ſufficient to prove, that <hi>W. P.</hi> do's not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>The Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173039:3"/> to be <hi>God,</hi> nor that Chriſt was wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our Tranſgreſſions, and bore our Griefs; nor deny that Jeſus Chriſt was the Son of God, that died at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> nor that we are Juſtified through the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; nor that Jeſus is the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Chriſt of God; or the Reſurrection of the Body; nor Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value the Scriptures: All which Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Hereſie and Error he pretends to find in the Books following, as they are Cited by him.</p>
            <p>His Firſt Quotation is out of <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 12, 13, 15. <hi>If God, as the Scriptures Teſtifie, hath never been declared or believed, but as the Holy One, then will it follow, that God is not a Holy Three, nor doth ſubſiſt in Three diſtinct or ſeparate Holy Ones; and ſince the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Spirit is God: Then unleſs the Father, Son and Spirit are Three diſtinct Nothings, they muſt be Three diſtinct Subſtances, and conſequently Three diſtinct Gods:</hi> Thus he. Now to give ſome Light in this matter, it may be convenient to give the Reader a Brief Account of the occaſion of this Book and method which the Author <hi>W. P.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173039:4"/> has taken in the Writing of it: As to the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The occaſion it was this, <hi>Thomas Vincent,</hi> in a Meeting of his, ſaid, <hi>That the</hi> Quakers <hi>held Damnable Doctrines. George Whitehead</hi> being preſent, ſtood up, and as it was his place, willingly would have given the People an Information of our Principles; which, if Objected againſt, he was ready to defend them by the Authority of Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which <hi>T. Vincent</hi> prevented, and put the following Queſtion: <hi>Whether we owned one Godhead Subſiſting in Three diſtinct and ſeparate Perſons?</hi> This was the occaſion of this Book, next as to the method it is this, <hi>W. P.</hi> refutes the the Doctrine built upon the fore-going Queſtion; firſt from Scripture, next from Right Reaſon; ſhewing many Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Irrational Conſequences flowing from that Doctrine; and all this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd with many Informations and Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning it. Now the two firſt Lines of <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Quotation are part of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawn from Scripture by <hi>W. P.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Doctrine in the Quotation above, and the reſt of that Quotation is part of one of thoſe Irreligious Conſequences which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173039:4"/> 
               <hi>W. P.</hi> ſhews in the Book before Cited, to be the reſult of the ſame Doctrine: But beſides this abuſive patching, and ſetting down as <hi>W. P</hi>'s Sentiment; what <hi>W. P.</hi> ſets down as an Irreligious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. <hi>T. B.</hi> does not come up to the Terms of Queſtion which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Three diſtinct and ſeparate Perſons Subſiſting in one God. If he can prove this from Scripture, then he proves what <hi>W. P.</hi> hath denied. But while <hi>T. Budd</hi> does only ſet down the Teſtimony of the Apoſtle, <hi>viz. That the Father, the Word, and the Spirit are the Three that bear Record in Heaven, and are One God.</hi> He does not at all ſhew himſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Queſtion in the Terms <hi>W. P.</hi> denies it. And for ſuch Holy Three, as is mentioned in Scripture, which have none of the Terms <hi>W. P.</hi> oppoſes, he hath ſufficiently ſhewn his Belief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not only in the Confeſſion of Faith hereafter mentioned, but alſo in his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency with Her open Face;</hi> and his <hi>Key.</hi> And many of his Books which do at all border upon that Point of Faith. This for <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s firſt Charge.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:173039:5"/>
            <p>His Second is, The Denial of Chriſt's Satisfaction; for Proof of which <hi>T. Budd</hi> hath made a Quotation out of the ſame Book, <hi>viz. Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 16, 18, 21, 22. <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Juſtice offended being Infinite, his Satisfaction ought to bear a proportion therewith, which</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>as Man, could never pay, he being Finite; and from a Finite Cauſe could not proceed an Infinite Effect—Since Chriſt could not pay what was not his own; it follows, that in the payment of his own, the Caſe ſtill remains equally grievous, ſince the Debt is not hereby abſolved or forgiven, but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd only; and by conſequence we are no better provided for Salvation than before, owing that now to the Son which was once owing to the Father. It no way renders Men beholding, or in the leaſt obliged to God, ſince by their Doctrine he would not have abated us, nor did he Chriſt the leaſt Farthing.</hi> Hitherto <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Quotation, but the Doctrine which <hi>W. P.</hi> does in the Pages before Cited oppoſe, is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by <hi>W. P.</hi> in p. 14. of <hi>Sandy Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> and is in the Terms following:</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:173039:5"/>
            <q>Doctr. <hi>That Man having Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Righteous Law of God, and ſo expoſed to the Penalty of Eternal Wrath, it's altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for God to remit or forgive without a plenary Satisfaction; and that there was no other way by which God could obtain Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſave Men, then by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting the Penalty of Infinite Wrath and Vengeance on Jeſus Chriſt the Second Perſon in the</hi> Trinity, <hi>who for Sins paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to come, hath wholly borne and paid it, to the offended Infinite Juſtice of his Father.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>AGainſt this Rigid and Unſcriptural Doctrine <hi>VV. P.</hi> brings about Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Texts of Scripture, and from them ſhews the great Forgiveneſs of God; after them in p. 17, 18. he refutes this Doctrine from Right Reaſon; ſhewing,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173039:6"/> why <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as Man, could not be a plenary Satisfaction; the place is thus, p. 18. 6. <hi>Tbe Juſtice Offended, being Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, his Satisfaction ought to bear a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion therewith, which Jeſus Chriſt, as Man, could never pay, he being Finite, and from a Finite Cauſe could not proceed an Infinite Effect; for ſo Man may be ſaid to bring forth God, ſince nothing below the Divinity of Chriſt it ſelf, can rightly be Stiled Infinite.</hi> Of this Reaſon <hi>T. Budd</hi> cut off the laſt Line. But to go on, <hi>W. P.</hi> having in this, and ſix or ſeven particulars more, ſhewn the contrariety of the Doctrine above, to Right Reaſon, he then numbers up nine Irreligious and Irrational Conſequences from the afore Doctrine: The ſeventh and eighth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences in p. 19. runs thus, <hi>Since Chriſt could not pay what was not his own, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that in the payment of his own, the caſe ſtill remains equally grievous; ſince the debt is not hereby abſolved or fogiven, but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd only; and by conſequence we are no better provided for Salvation than before; owing that now to the Son which was once owing to the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:173039:6"/>
            <p>8. <hi>It no way renders Man beholding, or in in the leaſt oblig'd to God, ſince by their Doctrine he would not have abated us, nor did he Chriſt the leaſt Farthing, ſo that the acknowledgments are peculiarly the Sons; which deſtroys the whole Current of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Teſtimony, for his good will towards Men. O the Infamous Portraiture, this Doctrine draws of the Infinite Goodneſs: Is this your Retribution? O Injurious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactioniſts.</hi> Of this, <hi>T. B.</hi> in his Quotation hath taken but about two Lines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. B</hi>'s Third Charge is, That <hi>W. P.</hi> hath denyed Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, that Died at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> his Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is out of <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> in Anſwer to <hi>T. Jenner,</hi> p. 146. <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>He</hi> (T. Jenner) <hi>takes up a whole Chapter in his endeavours to prove, That we deny the Lord that bought us, becauſe we deny that Perſon (the Son of God) that Died at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>to be our Redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be convenient here, to give ſome Brief Account of this Book, before I give the Quotation out of it, in order to its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Underſtanding, which in ſhort is this: This Book, Entituled, <hi>A Serious Apology,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:173039:7"/> &amp;c. was written by <hi>W. P.</hi> in Anſwer, and for the Clearing of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> from the Malicious Aſperſions, Erronious Doctrines, and Horid Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of <hi>Tho. Jenner</hi> and <hi>Timothy Taylor,</hi> in a Book of theirs, Entituled, <hi>Quakeriſm, Anatomized and Confuted:</hi> In which Book among other things they ſay, The <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> deny the Lord that brought them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In reply to this, <hi>W. P.</hi> in p. 146. of the <hi>Apology,</hi> ſays, <hi>1ſt. He takes up a whole Chapter in his endeavours to prove, that we deny the Lord that bought us, though very falſly, and with equal inſucceſs.</hi> And here he brings in a Quotation out of <hi>Quakeriſm Anatomized,</hi> &amp;c. p. 153, 154. The Quotation is thus out of <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Becauſe we deny that Perſon (the Son of God) that Dyed at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to be our Redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And immediately <hi>W. P.</hi> ſubjoyns, which moſt horid Imputation has been Anſwered more (I believe) than a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times; that is, <hi>That he that laid down his Life, and ſuffered his Body to be Crucified by the</hi> Jews, <hi>without the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>is Chriſt the only Son of the moſt High God: But that the outward</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:173039:7"/> 
               <hi>Perſon</hi> (or Body only, which is what <hi>VV. P.</hi> meant as appears by what follow) <hi>which Suffered was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny, and it is a perfect Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their own Principles;</hi> A Body haſt thou prepared me, <hi>ſaid the Son; then the Son was not the Body, though the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was the Sons; this brings him more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the charge of making him but a meer Man, than us, who acknowledge him to be One with the</hi> Father, <hi>and of a Nature Eternal and Immortal; for he was Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Father before the VVorld was.</hi> The Patching and Horrid Forgery of <hi>T. Budd</hi> in this place is ſurely without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, for here he has not been content only to pick a Line, but alſo to joyn to it (as <hi>VV. P</hi>'s, a Quotation which <hi>VV. P.</hi> took out of his Adverſaries Book to Anſwer as above. To this Forgery, he has alſo added Folly in that after pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two or three Lines of the laſt Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he has laid them down in his Sheet, as a Charge of a different Nature from the laſt mentioned, which he makes his Fifth Charge; but this his Folly, Blind Malice, and Forgery, falls back upon himſelf: Such is the Shame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173039:8"/> of him, and all others; who, by Apoſtatizing from the Spirit of Truth, are become Darkneſs. I proceed now to <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Fourth Charge, drawn out of p. 148. of this ſame Book, and which is, That <hi>VV. P.</hi> denies Juſtification by an Imputative Righteouſneſs</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Quotation runs thus, <hi>That we deny Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt hath fulfilled in his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for us (wholly without us) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deny the Lord that brought us.</hi> In Anſwer to this <hi>VV. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this we deny, and boldly affirm it, in the Name of the Lord, to be the Doctrine of</hi> Devils, <hi>and an Arm of the Sea of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which does now delude the whole VVorld. If Men may be Juſtified while Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, then God quits the Guilty. Death came by actual Sin, not imputative in his Senſe; therefore Juſtification unto Life, comes by Actual Righteouſneſs, not Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the <hi>Apology</hi> it appears: That <hi>VV. P.</hi> does in this Page of 148. bring a Quotation out of <hi>T. Jenner</hi>'s Book, p. 155, 156, 157, viz.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:173039:8"/>
            <q>That we deny Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt hath fulfilled in his own Perſon for us (wholly without us) and therefore deny the Lord that bought us.</q>
            <p>TO this <hi>VV. P.</hi> ſubjoyns, <hi>And indeed this we deny, and boldly affirm it in the Name of the Lord, to be the Doctrine of</hi> Devils, <hi>and an Arm of the Sea of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which does now deluge the wbole VVorld.</hi> And then goes on, <hi>I ſhall not ſo much inſiſt upon this, as I have not upon the other four particulars, they having been Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refutable Conſidered and Anſwered by my Friend and Partner in this Diſcourſe, in the firſt Part of this</hi> Apology: <hi>Only this I ſhall obſerve and add:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>No Man can be Juſtified without Faith</hi> (ſays <hi>Jenner)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Man hath</hi> Faith <hi>without</hi> Works <hi>(any more than a Body can Live without a Spirit</hi> (ſaith <hi>James)</hi> viz. the Apoſtle.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the VVorks of Righteouſneſs, by the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, are neceſſary to Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:173039:9"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>If Men may be Juſtified, whilſt impure, then God quits the Guilty; contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Scripture, which cannot be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Death came by Actual Sin, not Imputative in his Senſe; therefore Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification unto Life comes by Actual Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and not Imputative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are Three more Concluſions which follow, and which for brevity ſake, I omit, willing only to recite ſo much as may take in all that <hi>T. Budd</hi> has here and there pick'd to make up his Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, only next immediately after the Three Concluſions; which, I ſay, I have left out, there follows a ſhort Confeſſion of our Faith, which it may be of Service to the Honeſt-minded to publiſh; as alſo a Teſtimony againſt the Apoſtacy, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cricy and Envy of <hi>T. Budd,</hi> who could not but ſee it when he mangled that part of the Book, as he thought, for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: It is in p. 149. <hi>VVe do believe only in one Holy God Almighty, who is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit, the Creator of all Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his only Son, and Expreſs Image of his Subſtance, who took upon him Fleſh, and was in the VVorld, and in Life, Doctrine, Miracles, Death, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:173039:9"/> 
               <hi>Aſcenſion, and Mediation, perfectly did, and does continue to do the Will of God, to whoſe Holy Life, Power, Mediation and Blood, we only aſcribe our Sanctification, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Redemption and perfect Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And we believe in one Holy Spirit, that proceeds and breaths from the Father and the Son, as the Life and Virtue of both the Father and the Son, a meaſure of which is given to all, to profit with; and he that has One has all; for thoſe Three are One, who is the</hi> Alpha <hi>and the</hi> Ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, <hi>the Firſt and the Laſt, God over all, Bleſſed for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Sixth Charge againſt <hi>VV. P.</hi> is, <hi>The Denying the</hi> Meſſiah <hi>the Chriſt of God;</hi> for which he Cites a Book, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker;</hi> written by <hi>G. VV.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> againſt the Injurious Attempts of many Adverſaries; and it will ſtand againſt the weak, though black, Attempts of this Man, who in this Quotation of his, has with a hardned Face, cut a Sentence a-ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the midſt, which I queſtion whether any <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſitor has yet done, when he willingly raked in a Book for Hereſie; his Quotation is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173039:10"/> thus, <hi>Chr. Quaker,</hi> p. 96. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw my Day and Rejoyced: <hi>They ſtill harping upon that viſible Body, not Thirty Years Old, Replied,</hi> Thou art not yet Fifty, and haſt thou ſeen <hi>Abraham? Taking that to be the</hi> Meſſiah <hi>the Chriſt of God, and Saviour of the World;</hi> he meant, <hi>which they ſaw with their Carnal Eyes.</hi> I ſhall now give the Quotation from the Book it ſelf, but am obliged to Recite the whole Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph (the above Quotation being in the middle) and the whole being ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant upon every part, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without ſome hurt to the meaning of the whole, be ſeparated; it is thus, <hi>Chr. Quaker,</hi> p. 96. <hi>Before I conclude, take this notable ſaying of Chriſt to the Jews, and what may be collected from it to our purpoſe,</hi> Before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I am: <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw my Day and Rejoyced, <hi>John</hi> 8. 56, 57, 58. <hi>which affords us briefly thus much: That though he was not ſo viſibly come, yet it was the very ſame HE that came about One Thouſand Six Hundred Years ago, who was with the Fathers of Old; and that</hi> Abraham, <hi>who Lived Nineteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years before that outward Appearance, ſaw him, and his Day. If this be not the</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:173039:10"/> 
               <hi>import of the place, I know none; for the</hi> Jews, <hi>not believing him to be the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>thought it high Perſumption for him to compare with</hi> Abraham; Art thou greater than our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> who is Dead, and the Prophets are Dead? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which he anſwered (that he might prove himſelf to be the true</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>the Chriſt of God)</hi> (the foregoing part of this Sentence, as alſo the explanatory Parentheſis <hi>T. B.</hi> cut off, and begins his here) <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw my Day, and rejoyced: <hi>They ſtill harped upon that Viſible Body not Thirty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>three Years Old, replied,</hi> Thou art not yet Fifty, and haſt thou ſeen <hi>Abraham? Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that to be the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>the Chriſt of God, and Saviour of the World, he meant, which they ſaw with their Carnal Eyes. To which he rejoyned with a</hi> Verily, Verily, I ſay unto you, before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I am; then took they up Stones to caſt at him, &amp;c. <hi>By all which it is moſt clear, that unleſs our Adverſaries will deny him that ſo ſpoke (which yet</hi> T. Hicks<hi>'s Anti-Scriptural Opinion doth imply) to be Chriſt, who ſingled and diſtinguiſh'd himſelf as the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>the Chriſt of God, and Saviour of the World, from that Viſible Body, not</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:173039:11"/> 
               <hi>Fifty Years Old indeed; both Chriſt that ſpoke then muſt needs have been long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Time; and that ſuch Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ancients were not without a ſight and proſpect of him, and the day of his Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Appearance, or that moſt Signal Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of himſelf in that Body prepared for that Great and Holy Purpoſe, witneſs the exceeding Clear and Heavenly Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that were as ſo many Fore-runners or Introductions of the Evangelical State.</hi> This true Quotation does ſufficiently ſhew <hi>W. P.</hi> to own and believe in the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Chriſt of God.</p>
            <p>I come now to <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Seventh Charge, <hi>viz. Chriſt, the Son of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, denied by W. P. to be the Seed of the Promiſe.</hi> In this Charge <hi>T. Budd</hi> has hid his head; he having made a Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but named no Book, nor any Page where his (I doubt not) falſe Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be found; therefore I paſs it by without notice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Eighth Charge is, <hi>The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body denied by</hi> W. P. The Book he quotes is W. P<hi>'s Rejoynder to</hi> John Faldo, p. 369, 370. his Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion runs thus: <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:173039:11"/> J. F<hi>'s Relative (it) to hold, I do deny that this Text (viz.</hi> It is Sown a Natural Body, it is Raiſed a Spiritual Body) <hi>is concerned in the Reſurrection of Man's Carnal Body at all.—I ſay, this doth not concern the Reſurrection of Carnal Bodies, but the two States of Men under the firſt and Second</hi> Adam.</p>
            <p>In this, as in the former, he has plaid the Inquiſitor, taking here and there a Line, as beſt liked him; only his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may be more fairly made for clipping this than any of the former; for they were all Engliſh, but here is a little Greek and Latin; yet of the Engliſh he has not taken all he ought and might have done. I will Recite the two Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraphs out of which he has pillaged his Quotation. The Greek Text is firſt ſet down, and then the Latin Tranſlation, it runs thus, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 Cor. 15. 44. <hi>Seritur Corpus animale, reſuſcitatur cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſpirituale.</hi> i. e. A Natural Body is Sown, a Spiritual Body is Raiſed: <hi>That is, They lay down a Natural, and take up a Spiritual Body, or in lieu of a Natural receive a Spiritual Body; not that the</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:173039:12"/> 
               <hi>Natural Body ſhall be Tranſubſtantiated into a Spiritual Body, or that admitting of ſuch an exchange, that the Spiritual is the ſame Numerical Body, that was the Natural; for ſo the Natural and Spiritual Body would be one and the ſame; but ſuppoſe</hi> J. Faldo<hi>'s Relative (It) to hold, I do utterly deny that this Text is concerned in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Man's Carnal Body at all. I will Recite it with the five following Verſes as they lye in our Engliſh Tranſlation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſown a Natural Body, it is raiſed a Spiritual Body; there is a Natural Body, and there is a Spiritual Body; and ſo it is written, The firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> was made a Living Soul, the laſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made a Quickning Spirit; howbeit, that was not firſt which was Spiritual, but that which is Natural, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that which is Spiritual; the firſt Man is of the Earth, Earthy; the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is the Lord from Heaven; as is the Earthy, ſo are they that are Earthy; and as is the Heavenly, ſo are they alſo which are Heavenly; and as we have born the Image of the Earthy, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly, <hi>Verſe</hi> 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49. <hi>I ſay, this doth not</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:173039:12"/> 
               <hi>concern the Reſurrection of Carnal Bodies, but the two States of Men under the Firſt and Second</hi> Adam, <hi>Men are Sown into the World Natural, and ſo they are the Sons of the Firſt</hi> Adam. <hi>but they are Raiſed Spiritually, through him who is the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and the Life, and ſo they are the Sons of the Second</hi> Adam, <hi>the Lord from Heaven, the Quickning Spirit. The very words of the Apoſtle undeniably prove this to be the Scope; how elſe could the Firſt</hi> Adam<hi>'s being made a Living Soul, and the Second</hi> Adam <hi>a Quickning Spirit, be a Pertinent Inſtance to prove Natural and Spiritual Bodies; upon which follows,</hi> that the Natural was Firſt; <hi>that is, the Firſt</hi> Adam; <hi>and then that which is Spiritual,</hi> which is the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit, the Lord from Heaven, <hi>who came to raiſe up the Sons of the Firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>from their Dead to his Living, their Natural to his Spiritual, State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now given the Paragraphs intire, out of which <hi>T. Budd</hi> had pickt his Quotation, and which does ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Confute the wrong Suggeſtions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I may not well omit to take ſome little notice of his Reply to the above
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173039:13"/> Quotation: It is thus, <hi>Therefore let</hi> P. W. <hi>know,</hi> &amp;c. (he has forgot to place the Letters right) I can aſſure <hi>T. Budd</hi> that <hi>W. P.</hi> does know, and believe the good Doctrine of Chriſt's Crucifixion, and the advantages of a true Chriſtian upon it; and I can alſo aſſure <hi>T. Budd,</hi> that I look upon him no more Cordial an Adviſer to <hi>W. P.</hi> than Satan was to our Saviour, when he repeated the Text to him, <hi>And he hath given his Angels Charge over thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>T. Budd</hi> hath done with Adviſing, and now Threatens: <hi>And if he thinks to ſtop our Teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c. And I do tell <hi>T. Budd,</hi> that if he thinks to go on without Oppoſition in Forgery and Wreſting, then I think he will find himſelf miſtaken, ſince we have <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s advice for to uſe the Rod: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Night is ſo far ſpent, and the Day ſo dawned, as ſufficiently diſcovers where to apply it. But now <hi>T. Budd</hi> would appear one that can Calculate Myſteries, and point at a Beaſt by its number; but if he will take the Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Letters of his own Name, he will find he makes up Three times that Beaſt, and Seven to ſpare. As for what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173039:13"/> he Promiſes for the Year 1700 and 1750, I can without ſuch Calculation tell him, That let the freedom of the Upright-hearted and Faithful towards God be as in his Divine Wiſdom he ſhall ſee meet; yet <hi>T. Budd,</hi> with all that Apoſtatize from the Spirit of Chriſt, and turn their backs upon his Holy Law, will ſtill be in ſevereſt Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>I now come to his laſt Charge againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> which is, <hi>That he hath <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued the Scriptures.</hi> The Book <hi>T. Budd</hi> quotes, is <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> p. 144. 142. (I am not to account for his Folly in Poſtponeing the bigger number) his Quotation is thus: <hi>Chriſt left nothing in Writing, as the Rule that we hear of; and doubtleſs had he intended the Rule of his Followers to have been a Written Rule, he would have left it upon Record with all Punctuality; this muſt be believed, and that done on pain of Eternal Death. If the Scriptures were the Rule of Faith and Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then becauſe they cannot be the Rule in their Tranſlations, ſuppoſe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Copies were exact, it cannot be the Rule to far the greateſt part of Mankind;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:173039:14"/> 
               <hi>indeed to none but Learned Men.</hi> In this part of the Book <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> come to ſpeak concerning the Scriptures, which were aſſerted to them, to be a <hi>General and Perfect Rule of Faith and Life (viz.</hi> to all Men) they have divers Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſhew the contrary; their Eighth Argument lies thus: 8. <hi>Furthermore, if the Scriptures were the Rule of Faith and Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then becauſe they cannot be the Rule in their Tranſlations, ſuppoſe the Antient Copies were exact, it cannot be the Rule to far the greateſt part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, indeed to none but Learned Men; which neither anſwers the Promiſe relating to Goſpel times that is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, nor the neceſſity of all Mankind for a Rule of Faith and Life.</hi> (Here he cut off the concluſion of this Argument) In p. 144. There is another Objection thus, <hi>But if the Law engraven and delivered to</hi> Moſes <hi>was a Rule to the</hi> Jews, <hi>why ſhould not the Law delivered by Chriſt, and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his Apoſtles, be the Rule to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this it is Anſwered,</p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Chriſt left nothing in Writing as the Rule, that we hear of; and it is</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:173039:14"/> 
               <hi>not to be thought he was leſs Faithful in his Houſe than</hi> Moſes (This laſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>T. Budd</hi> cut out) <hi>and doubtleſs had he intended the Rule of his Followers to have been a Written Rule, he would have left it upon Record with all Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuality, This muſt be believed and that done, on pain of Eternal Death</hi> (what follows <hi>T. Budd</hi> has cut off) <hi>Nor did his followers Write in the Method of a Rule, as the Law was Written; nor did they ſo Call or Recommend what they Writ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now done with all the Falſe Charges of <hi>T. Budd</hi> upon <hi>W. P.</hi> and put the ſeveral Quotations in their true Light, from whence the Unprejudiced Reader may make a Solid Judgment of them. I ſhall in few words beſpeak the Readers Patience, while I more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſpeak concerning this <hi>T. Budd,</hi> who was in Unity of Profeſſion with <hi>W. P.</hi> divers Years after all the Books afore-cited by him were VVritten; and in which he now pretends to find ſuch Errors and Hereſies, and I doubt not was acquainted with all, or a great
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173039:15"/> part of them: But now (like <hi>Eve)</hi> his Eyes being opened, he is become a Man of <hi>Gath,</hi> one who gives Information to all (as himſelf ſays) who ſeek after Truth and Righteouſneſs; but which, I am ſure, is not to be found in this his Teſtimony, nor in any Teſtimony that ever was given forth by the Spirit of Apoſtacy, in which he is. He calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>A Servant of Chriſt.</hi> To this his Claim it may be proper to ask him the Queſtion which was put to the Man in the Goſpel; <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> It is but a few Years ſince he made publick Profeſſion of what he now calls Errors and Hereſies; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is very great betwixt the Erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Heretick, and him who is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Servant of Chriſt; and we have not ſeen any marks of Repentance and Recantation, in order to this his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reſtoration; and it is not to be allowed in the Nature and Order of Converſion, for a Man who hath through Ignorance embraced Error, and through the viciouſneſs of his VVill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Hereſie, to become reallya Servant of Chriſt, and a True Member of a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173039:15"/> Chriſtian Society without deep Sorrow, hearty Repentance, and great Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of God's Goodneſs, and his own former Vileneſs and Ignorance; of all which we have heard nothing, but have often heard, that like the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee,</hi> he is crying out, <hi>I am more Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous than thou;</hi> from whence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude he is at great diſtance from a true Poſſeſſion of this Claim. I ſhall now, honeſt Reader, give thee a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, only deſiring that the Quotations truly made may be to thy Edification, as the Detection of <hi>T. Budd</hi>'s Fraud will be, I hope, to thy Satisfaction.</p>
            <trailer>THE END</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
